Finding Aid for Richard B. Brandt papers 1935-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard B. Brandt papers 1935-1996, 1955-1992
Brandt, Richard B.
7.5 linear feet
Philosopher and ethicist, professor at the University of Michigan 1964-1981, papers include notes, writings, course materials and correspondence.
9873 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Karen Brandt in 1998. (Donor no. 8679 )
The papers are open to research.
Richard B. Brandt (1935-1996), one of the most influential moral philosophers of the second half of the twentieth century, taught at the University of Michigan for seventeen years, assuming chairmanship of the Department of Philosophy upon his arrival in 1964. During his academic career, he was a fellow of the Guggenheim Foundation, a fellow at the Center for Advanced Studies in Behavioral Sciences, Stanford, California, and a Senior Fellow of the National Endowment for the Humanities. He served as President of the American Philosophical Association, western division, and was a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. A prolific writer, Brandt authored nearly one hundred articles and six books. In 1974, he was selected to give the John Locke lectures at Oxford University, which became the basis for A Theory of the Good and the Right published in 1979, considered his crowning achievement in ethics.
Brandt was born in Wilmington, Ohio on October 17, 1910 and graduated from Denison University in 1930. Following graduation, he studied at Trinity College, Cambridge University, where he received a BA in 1934, followed by two years of study at Tuebingen University. After returning to the United States, he received his Ph.D. in Philosophy from Yale University in 1936. He taught philosophy at Swarthmore College before coming to Michigan, where he was later named the Roy Wood Sellars Distinguished College Professor of Philosophy. Although he retired in 1977, Brandt continued to teach as visiting professor at the Institute for Philosophy and Public Affairs at the University of Maryland, Florida State University, the Georgetown University Law Center, and University of California-Irvine.
Brandt's major philosophical interests were in ethics and in the nature and origin of knowledge. He also had strong interests in psychology and anthropology as they influenced or reflected ethical values - evidenced particularly in his 1954 publication Hopi Ethics: A Theoretical Analysis which was based upon meticulous research in Arizona on the Hopi people. Brandt's interest in drawing upon a vast range of learning expanded the scope of contemporary philosophy. In modern psychology, for example, he explored theories of motivation, learning and psychotherapy.
Unconfined to traditional foundations of ethics, Brandt worked on a wide range of philosophical problems and on public moral issues such as suicide, the rules of war, defective newborns, and welfare policies. According to a colleague, Brandt insisted that, "Traditional philosophical questions ... are often confused, and a philosopher must work to identify what is clear and important in them... [Brandt] rejected appeals to 'intuition,' and worked to find better ways to support philosophical conclusions. [He] was creative and insightful in reformulating questions, proposing solutions to them and arguing for his positions ... always determined to get to the root of an issue." Decision making for complex problems, according to Brandt, is time consuming, but as the proverb goes, "Decide in haste, repent at leisure."
Brandt's theory of the good and the right, which evolved over several decades and appeared at various stages of its evolution in numerous articles and two major books, was intended to address - and to recommend itself - to the present age. In 1959, he set forth in Ethical Theory his highly regarded form of rule-utilitarianism. Rule-utilitarianism, a leading theory of moral right and wrong, bases answers to questions essentially on the benefits that flow from the widespread acceptance of moral rules in a society - a moral system that is "welfare maximizing" (which Brandt believed carries inherent implications for law and government). The volume, considered a primary source in moral philosophy, was translated into Italian, Spanish and Polish. In a second book, A Theory of the Good and the Right published in 1979, Brandt asked, "Why should philosophers not actively introduce definitions which enable people to think more clearly and disabuse them of misconception?" One of the clarifying functions of a philosopher Brandt believed, is to offer more precise and useful definitions of words. It was his view that the philosopher can play a useful role by evaluating and ordering the philosophical principles underlying function, including, for example, legislation. "Taking a broad view," he said, "could have spin-offs -- suggest options which otherwise would not have been thought of, or make the dilemmas seem less serious by placing them in perspective."
Brandt's last monograph Facts, Values and Morality was published just a year before he died in 1996. In a University Record tribute in 1997, Allan F. Gibbard, the Richard B. Brandt Distinguished Professor of Philosophy, spoke to Brandt's contribution to philosophical scholarship: "Richard Brandt was one of the most eminent and influential moral philosophers of his generation. His books were landmarks, and he was prolific with important articles to the very end of his long life. His writing was always careful and clear, trenchant and imaginative."
Richard Brandt delighted in discussion on wide ranging issues with department colleagues and with those from other disciplines and in the community. He was a lunch-time regular from its inception at the "Ethics Roundtable," a weekly discussion group at the Michigan League, which he initially organized. Brandt had a son, Richard, a daughter, Karen, and two grandchildren, Jared and Kristen.
The Richard B. Brandt papers span the years 1935 to 1996, however the bulk of the collection covers the years 1955 to 1992. Except for the removal from the collection of a large amount of printed material that was not Brandt's work, the papers reflect the content and filing orientation maintained by him. There are six series in the collection: Biographical; Articles and Manuscripts; Course Material; Research Notes; Topical Files; and Correspondence.
The collection is primarily comprised of papers which document the breadth and depth of Brandt's investigations into philosophical questions -- including notes, writings, commentary on collected works of others, and teaching materials. Except for a few correspondence files, there is little of a personal nature, and there are no records representing Brandt's tenure as chair of the Philosophy Department at the University of Michigan. Papers include detailed course materials (particularly on moral philosophy); published and unpublished writings on a range of philosophical issues; and extensive commentary on readings. Researchers should note that there is considerable overlap between the various series. Correspondence, for example, is often associated with an article or included in a topical file; research notes and topical files frequently contain similar subject matter; and articles and manuscripts sometimes include research notes. These overlaps are evidence of Brandt's integrated approach to his life's work -- research, teaching, and writing, as well as much of his correspondence, each influencing and informing the other.
Subjects:
Brandt, Richard B.; Ethics.; Hopi Indians.; Philosophy--Study and teaching.; Philosophy--Outlines, syllabi, etc.; Philosophy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Biographical
  The Biographical Series contains just one folder, but is important for the data it holds outlining the evolution of Brandt's career through teaching posts, fellowships and publications. In addition to vitae and publication lists, the file includes newspaper articles written at the time of his death and a photographic snapshot.
  - Clippings and vita, 1 folder (Box 1)
- Articles and Manuscripts, 0.75 linear feet
  The Articles and Manuscripts series is arranged alphabetically by title. Brandt wrote regularly, resulting in more than one hundred articles published in Ethics Journal of Philosophy Philosophical Review Mind The Monist Law and Philosophy and other professional journals. The series contains reprints, drafts, outlines, as well as comments, critiques and correspondence from colleagues for approximately half of this output. There are also folders of book reviews written by Brandt and reviews of several of Brandt's books written by others.
  - "Appraisal of a Morality," 1994 (Box 1)
  - Bentham, Jeremy (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews by Brandt 1952-1983 (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews of Brandt's Work 1955-1992 (Box 1)
  - "Concept of a Moral Right and Its Function" 1983 (Box 1)
  - "Concept of a Rational Final End" (Box 1)
  - "Concept of Rational Belief," 1979 (Box 1)
  - "Concept of Welfare," 1966 (Box 1)
  - "Concepts of Obligation and Duty," 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Conscience (Rule) Utilitarianism and the Criminal Law," 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Czy wybor systemu moralnego...," 1973 (Box 1)
  - "Did Parfait Defeat the Self-Interest Theory?" 1992 (Box 1)
  - "Emotive Theory of Ethics," 1950 (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia of Philosophy: "Ethical Relativism;" "Epistemology and Ethics," 1967 (Box 1)
  - "Epistemological Status of Memory Beliefs," 1955 (Box 1)
  - "Foundationalism for Moral Theory," circa 1977 (Box 1)
  - "Future of Ethics" (Box 1)
  - "Ideal Observer Theory" (Box 1)
  - "Indirect Consequentialism and Friendship," circa 1995 (Box 1)
  - "Interpersonal Comparison of Utility," 1993 (Box 1)
  - "Is Ethics a Science?" 1980 (Box 1)
  - "Justification of Epistemic Statements: A Parallel with Ethics" (Box 1)
  - "Languages of Realism and Nominalism," 1957 (Box 1)
  - "Logic of Ethics and Science" (Box 1)
  - "Logic of Moral Relativism" (Box 1)
  - "Logic of the Identity Theory" 1967 (Box 1)
  - "Moral Valuation," 1946 (Box 1)
  - "Morality and Its Critics," 1988 (Box 1)
  - "Morality of Abortion," 1972 (Box 1)
  - Outlines: Chapters (Box 1)
  - "Overvold on Self-Interest and Self-Sacrifice," 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - "Personality Traits as Casual Explanations in Biography" (Box 1)
  - Price, Henry H. (Box 1)
  - Queries About Rawl's Theories of Justice (Box 1)
  - "Rational Desires," circa 1970 (Box 1)
  - "Rationality, Egoism, and Morality," 1972 (Box 1)
  - "Real and Alleged Problems of Utilitarianism," 1982 (Box 1)
  - "Reply to Critics at APA Symposium," 1972 (Box 1)
  - "Roderick Firth's Contribution to Ethics" (Box 1)
  - "Rule Utilitarian Morality and the Criminal Law" (Box 1)
  - "Science as a Basis for Moral Theory," 1994 (Box 1)
  - "Science as a Basis for Theories of the Intrinsically Good," 1995 (Box 1)
  - "Science of Man and Wide Reflective Equilibrium," 1989 (Box 1)
  - "Science, Values, Morality," circa 1993 (Box 1)
  - "Self Interest and One's Own Good," circa 1996 (Box 1)
  - "Some Merits of One Form of Rule Utilitarianism," circa 1996 (Box 1)
  - "Strategy for Normative Ethics," 1974 (Box 1)
  - Sturgeon, Comments on... (Box 1)
  - "Traits of Character and Moral Assessment" (Box 1)
  - "Two Concepts of Utility" (Box 1)
  - Unpublished Papers (Box 1)
  - "Utilitarian Theory of Excuses," 1969 (Box 1)
  - "Utilitarianism and the Informed Desire Theory of the Good," circa 1975 (Box 1)
  - "Utilitarianism's Alleged Merging of Persons" (Box 1)
  - "Wants as Explanations of Actions," 1963 (Box 1)
- Course Material, 1.75 linear feet
  The Course Material, while inadequately representing the extent of Brandt's teaching over many years in its scope, unmistakably documents the discriminating care he took in preparing lectures, syllabi, reading lists, and exams. Detail is particularly rich in files he maintained for teaching moral philosophy, introduction to philosophy, and classic problems. Researchers interested in Brandt's theories related to the philosophy of law will want to review the file for the seminar in that topic he taught at Georgetown University Law Center in 1979. The series also holds notes on a course in economic theory he audited while on the faculty at Swarthmore.
  - Classic Problems (Box 1)
  - Contemporary Problems (Box 1)
    (Includes Memory and Other Minds)
  - Economic Theory, Mathematics for... (Swarthmore College) 1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ethics (Box 1)
  - Ethics and Theology (Box 1)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, scattered (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Syllabi (Box 2)
  - Moral Philosophy, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Moral Philosophy Notes, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Moral Philosophy, Blameworthiness, Reward and Punishment (Box 2)
  - Moral Systems (Box 2)
  - Moral Systems / Choices (Box 2)
  - Normative Ethics (Box 2)
  - Philosophical Problems in Psychology, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Philosophy of Law (Box 2)
  - Philosophy of Mind, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Political Theory (Box 2)
  - Problems and Principles (Box 2)
  - Social Philosophy, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Social Philosophy (Box 3)
  - Theory of Knowledge, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Value (Box 3)
- Research Notes, 2 linear feet
  Of particular significance in the Research Notes series are eight folders of documents (interviews, correspondence, statistical data, etc.) and two expandable folders of note cards produced during Brandt's extensive study of morality in the Hopi Indians. Brandt published Hopi Ethics: A Theoretical Analysis in 1954. It grew, he once wrote, out of an interest in the absolutist views of moral judgments held by psychologists K. Duncker, W. Koehler, and S.E. Asch. Brandt traced the evolution of his influential Theory of the Good and the Right (1979) back over several decades to this study. From this work on the Hopi evolved an interest in rule-utilitarianism, followed by studies in the psychology of motivation (eventually pursued at Stanford University), and leading to the John Locke lectures that were revised and incorporated for the text of Theory of the Good and the Right.
  In addition to the Hopi material, there is much more in this series that offers insight into Brandt's thinking. For example, there are several folders of notes he took on readings over the years, including two folders of recorded comments removed from books (by the departmental librarian) that were on his office shelves when he died. In the same regular hand are notebooks he kept that date back to student days at Yale and Cambridge.
  - Conferences
    - In Honor of Richard M. Hare 1994 (Box 3)
    - NEH Seminar on Plausibility of Utilitarianism 1977 (Box 3)
    - Northwestern 1967 (Box 3)
    - Preferences (Germany) 1992, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Descartes (Box 3)
  - Eskimo Study (Box 3)
  - Frankena, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Hopi Study, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Hopi Study Note Cards, 2 expandable folders (Box 4)
  - Hume (Box 4)
  - Kant (Box 4)
  - Leibnitz (Box 4)
  - Locke (Box 4)
  - Notebooks (7): Notes circa 1935-1952 (Box 4)
  - Notes on Readings (found in books) (Box 4)
  - On Readings, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Philosophy of Religion (Box 5)
  - Philosophy of Science (Box 5)
  - Rawls (Box 5)
  - Spinoza (Box 5)
- Topical, 2.5 linear feet
  The Topical files, the largest series in the collection, most effectively provide a window into Brandt's broad range of interests and concerns. Comprised of various writings, his own and others, as well as collected articles and newspaper clippings, drafts, and notes, the files encompass classical philosophical subjects as well as contemporary topics such as suicide, war, abortion, medicine and ethics. Here the researcher will also find material Brandt gathered, kept, and annotated from the realms of psychology and anthropology.
  - Abortion (Box 5)
  - Abortion Therapy (Box 5)
  - Abortion, Hare on... (Box 5)
  - Anthropology and Ethics (Box 5)
  - Approval (Box 5)
  - Basic Propositions (Box 5)
  - Basics (Box 5)
  - Behavior (Box 5)
  - Blanchard, Professor, Questions (Box 5)
  - Bond, E. J. (Box 5)
  - Character (Box 5)
  - Classic, Outlines (Box 5)
  - Concept of Morality (Box 5)
  - Concept of Utility (Box 5)
  - Concepts, Two, of Utilitarianism (Box 5)
  - Contemporary Scene in Moral Philosophy (Box 5)
  - Determinism (Box 5)
  - Development (Box 5)
  - Egoism and Moore (Box 5)
  - Emotion / Pleasure (Box 5)
  - Emotive Theory (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia Articles on Ethics and on Duty (Box 5)
  - Empiricist Theory of Meaning (Box 5)
  - Ethics (Box 6)
  - Evidence (Box 6)
  - Fairness to Happiness (Box 6)
  - Good (Box 6)
  - Good and Right, Theory of (Box 6)
  - Good Theory (Box 6)
  - Hansen and Mao Tzu (Box 6)
  - Hare, Hume, Hallaway and Hall (Box 6)
  - Immigration (Box 6)
  - Impartiality (Box 6)
  - Induction, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Insanity (Box 6)
  - Intentionality and Intentional Behavior, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Interpersonal Comparison of Utility (Box 6)
  - Justice (Box 6)
  - Legal Excuses (Box 6)
  - Logic (Box 6)
  - Logical Problems (Box 6)
  - Meaning and Justification in Ethics (Box 6)
  - Meaning, Analysis of (Box 6)
  - Mind Body Problem (Box 6)
  - Medicine and Ethics (Box 6)
  - Mill, J.S. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Topical Notes, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Moral Epistemology (Box 6)
  - Moral Realism (Box 6)
  - Moral Value / Naturalism (Box 6)
  - Motivation (Box 6)
  - Negative Utilitarianism (Box 6)
  - Non-Inductive Hypotheses (Box 6)
  - Non-Naturalism (Box 6)
  - Nuclear (Box 7)
  - Obligation (Box 7)
  - Patient Autonomy (Box 7)
  - Personality Traits (Box 7)
  - Political Theory (Box 7)
  - Promises (Box 7)
  - Psychology (Box 7)
  - Psychophysical Supervenience (Box 7)
  - Psychotherapy (Box 7)
  - Punishment (Box 7)
  - Rational Final End (Box 7)
  - Rationality, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Rawls and Intuition (Box 7)
  - Rawls' Theory of Justice (Box 7)
  - Relativism (Box 7)
  - Rights (Box 7)
  - Self-Realization (Box 7)
  - Sharp, Frank (Box 7)
  - Social Philosophy, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Sturgeon, Nicholas L. (Box 7)
  - Suicide (Box 7)
  - Theological Studies (Box 7)
  - Torts and Moral Theories (Box 7)
  - Universals (Box 7)
  - Theological Studies (Box 7)
  - Utilitarian Generalization (Box 7)
  - Utilitarianism (Box 7)
  - Value and Value Measurement, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Virtue and Truth (Box 7)
  - Welfare Economics (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 0.5 linear feet
  Correspondence, while slight, includes incoming and outgoing from the 1950s through the 1990s -- essentially communications worldwide with colleagues and former students, generally regarding or discussing his work or theirs. There is one folder of several letters that originally arrived on a computer disc. Material was printed-out from a Macintosh computer; the disc is also housed in the folder.
  - 1950s (Box 8)
  - 1960s (Box 8)
  - 1970s (Box 8)
  - 1980s (Box 8)
  - undated (Box 8)
  - Print-outs from computer disc